#大家好 現在天氣很熱哦
Hi everyone! It's very hot these days.
#外面都三十六七度
It's like 36 or 37 degrees outside.
#這裡面也將近
Even here inside it's still,
#將近二十九度到三十度左右
almost 29 or 30 degrees.
#你看 竹鼠睡覺都是
Look! The bamboo rats are
#反過來睡
sleeping upside down.
#你看 這個 就像中暑了一樣
Look! This one looks like having a heat stroke
#軟線線的
It's downy and soft.
#其實它是睡著啦
But in fact it's just sleeping.
#我抱起它來 它都不知道
It's knows nothing even I am now holding it.
#還在做夢
It's even having a dream.
#你有那麼累嗎
Are you really that tired?
#昨天晚上去幹嘛啦
What have you been doing last night?
#是不是去偷牛啦
Did you go to steal the cows?
#哎喲 起來啦 哎喲
Ayo! It wakes up! Ayo!
#哎喲 嚇到我啦
Ayo! It scared me.
#你看
Look!
#它一 一下子 在夢中驚醒
It sud, suddenly wakes up with a start.
#你看 它都想咬我啦
Look! It wants to bite me.
#你看 這是公的哦
Look! This is male.
#那麼大條 這個
It's so big, this one.
#四斤多哦 這個 將近五斤
It's more than 2 kg, almost 2 and a half.
#好結實啊 這個
It's very muscular and firm.
#很強壯的哦
It's very strong too.
#放回去
Put it back
#這個小胖
This is small Fatty.
#小胖
Small Fatty!
#哇
Wa!
#你胖啦 小胖
You're getting fat, Small Fatty
#你又胖啦
You get fat again.
#它尾巴 好多 (註︰說到一半沒了，不知原本想說甚麼)
It's tail. There's a lot of...
#你看 小胖 它現在比我都還老實啦
Look! Small Fatty is now even more gentle than I am.
#不動啦
It's not moving.
#好溫柔啦
So gentle and nice.
#呵呵 把你拎起來
Ho ho, I hold you up.
#你看 它這個腳
Look! Its feet
#回去
Back to the cell!
#你看 這個公的
Look! This male rat...
#哇 那麼大條
Wa! It's so big.
#像不像兔子
Does it look like a bunny?
#哦 現在 (註︰又是說到一半沒了)
Oh! Now...
#鼻子 鼻子嘟嘟嘟嘟的 (註︰甚麼叫鼻子嘟嘟嘟嘟？)
Its nose, its nose is like, "doo doo doo doo".
#呵呵
Ho ho
#好大個啊 這個
It's really huge, this rat.
#你看 這公的
Look! Is this male rat,
#這公的是不是中暑啦
Is it having a heat stroke?
#沒有
No.
#它好好的
It's in good condition.
#嚇到它啦
I scared it.
#你看 這公的好苗條哦
Look! This male rat is very slim.
#有點瘦 我給它加強營養
It's even a bit skinny. I may need to strengthen its nutrition.
#給它補一補
Make sure it's well fed.
#哦 今天晚上給你加餐
Oh! You'll have an extra meal tonight.
#吃胖一點哦
Eat more!
#你看 這個大胖
Look! This Big Fatty.
#哇 現在怎麼它那麼兇啦
Wa! Why is it so fierce now?
#現在大胖都瘦啦
Big Fatty is getting skinny now.
#跟小胖差不多啦
It's now not much fatter than Small Fatty.
#可能天氣熱 食欲不好
Perhaps the hot weather is affecting its appetite.
#我把它放回去
Let me put it back.
#你在幹嘛 在叫 叫的那麼慘
What's happened to you? How come you are creaking, creaking so miserably?
#叫
Creak!
#好啦 今天的視頻到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
#這個夏天的溫度哇
Make sure that the temperature
#千萬不要超過三十二度 三十三度哇
never exceeds 32, 33 degrees during the summer.
#這個
I mean
#廠房裡面
inside the shed.
#一般都沒 不會中暑的
Then the rats do not...I mean hardly have any heat stroke.
#如果超過這個溫度的話就有點危 危險哦
It might be a bit dangerous if the temperature exceeds this, this limit.